ORCID: 0000-0002-0092-6298 ResearcherID: <u>D-2885-2011</u> SCOPUS Author ID: <u>53877736300</u> ImpactStory: 0000-0002-0092-6298

# Juan David Leongómez

Ph.D., M.Sc.

Investigador en áreas de comportamiento y evolución humana. Mis intereses generales se centran en la comunicación vocal, principalmente en humanos, pero incluyendo otros mamíferos y aves. Así mismo, tengo interés en la percepción sonora, los mecanismos de selección de pareja, las relaciones entre hormonas y comportamiento, y los métodos experimentales y cuantitativos de investigación.

# EXPERIENCIA LABORAL

2018 – presentee

#### INVESTIGADOR POSTDOCTORAL – Universidad El Bosque

- + Financiación de Colciencias para el desarrollo del proyecto Señales perceptibles de salud física y mental en rostros, voces y olores corporales, y su relación con niveles hormonales.
- + Investigador del Laboratorio de Análisis del Comportamiento Humano (<u>LACH</u>).

2015 – presente

# ASSISTANT PROFESSOR - Universidad El Bosque, Faculty of Psychology

- + Investigador del Laboratorio de Análisis del Comportamiento Humano (LACH).
- + Asesor metodológico y estadístico de proyectos de profesores y estudiantes de postgrado.
- + Líder del grupo Colciencias <u>Procesos Cognoscitivos y Educación</u> (2016-2017, 2019 presente).
- + Organizador de la serie de conferencias semanales de la Facultad de Psicología Café Nerd (2016-2017).
- + Supervisión de diversos Proyectos de Grado asociados a proyectos en Psicología y Biología.
- + Supervision de Estudiantes Doctorales
  - Milena Vásquez-Amézquita (PhD en Neurociencias, <u>Universidad</u> de Valencia, España – 2015-2018. Supervisor Principal: <u>Prof. Alicia</u> <u>Salvador</u>).
  - Francisco Javier Flores (Professional Doctorate in Counselling <u>Psychology</u>, University of East London, Reino Unido. Supervisor <u>Principal: Dr Lisa Chiara Fellin</u>).

#### Clases dictadas

- + Métodos Cuantitativos I (Maestría en Psicología 2017).
- + Métodos Cuantitativos II (Maestría en Psicología 2017-presente)
- + Proyecto de Grado de Investigación I (2017).

+ Fuentes y Normas de Documentación en Psicología (2015).

#### 2015 - 2016

# PROFESOR CATEDRÁTICO – <u>La Sabana University</u>, <u>Faculty of Psychology</u>

## Modules taught

- + Evolución y Desarrollo de la Comunicación Vocal: Cantos, Modas y Lenguaje (2016).
- + Estadística Inferencial (2015-2016).
- + Estadística Descriptiva (2015-2016).

#### 2011 - 2014

## ASISTENTE DE ENSEÑANZA – University of Stirling (Escocia, Reino Unido).

- + Profesor Comportamiento Animal (cátedra en comunicación vocal).
- + Profesor Cognición (liderando proyectos de investigación er psicoacústica).
- + Profesor Métodos Cuantitativos de Investigación para el nivel de maestría (cátedras, supervisión en las clases prácticas, y aulas de apoyo individual).
- + Supervisión de proyecto de maestría (Evolutionary Psychology MSc).

# EDUCACIÓN

#### 2010 - 2014

## Ph.D. PSYCHOLOGY – University of Stirling (Reino Unido).

Behaviour and Evolution Research Group

Division of Psychology – School of Natural Sciences

- + Tesis Contextual Musicality: Vocal Modulation and its Perception in Human Social Interaction (http://dspace.stir.ac.uk/handle/1893/21102).
- + Supervisor Principal: Prof. S. Craig Roberts (www.scraigroberts.com).
- + Supervisor Secundario: Dr Anthony C. Little (<u>www.alittlelab.com</u>).

#### 2008 - 2009

#### M.Sc. EVOLUTIONARY PSYCHOLOGY - University of Liverpool (Reino Unido).

Behavioural Ecology and Evolutionary Psychology Research Group School of Biological Sciences

- + Tesis Variation of pitch and loudness range of human voice in response to intra- and inter-sexual stimuli.
- Módulos incluidos: Cognitive Evolution, Human Behavioural Ecology, Principles of Evolution, Statistics for Biologists, Early Humans: Sites and Behaviour.
- + Supervisor: Dr S. Craig Roberts (<u>www.scraigroberts.com</u>)

#### 1998 – 2005

# PEDAGOGÍA MUSICAL – Universidad Pedagógica Nacional.

Facultad de Bellas Artes

# BECAS, PREMIOS Y DISTINCIONES

2017	COLCIENCIAS - Convocatoria programa de Estancias Postdoctorales
	beneficiarios Colciencias 2017 (Investigador Principal: Juan David Leongómez).
	UNIVERSIDAD EL BOSQUE — Novena convocatoria interna para la financiación
	de proyectos de investigación e innovación tecnológica de la Universidad El
	Bosque, año 2017 (Investigador Principal: Oscar R. Sánchez Rubio).
2016	UNIVERSIDAD EL BOSQUE – Octava convocatoria interna para la financiación
	de proyectos de investigación e innovación tecnológica de la Universidad El
	Bosque, año 2016 (Investigador Principal: Dr Eugenio Valderrama Escallón).
2015	UNIVERSIDAD EL BOSQUE – Séptima convocatoria interna para la financiación
	de proyectos de investigación e innovación tecnológica de la Universidad El
	Bosque, año 2015 (Investigador Principal: Juan David Leongómez).
2014	EXPERIMENTAL PSYCHOLOGY SOCIETY - Grindley Grants (Investigador
	Principal: Juan David Leongómez).
2013	INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR HUMAN ETHOLOGY (ISHE) - Owen Aldis
	Award (Investigador Principal: Dr. Jakub Binter).
2010	COLCIENCIAS – Becas Francisco José de Caldas para estudios doctorales.
2009	SCHOOL OF BIOLOGICAL SCIENCES - UNIVERSITY OF LIVERPOOL - Annual
	Prize in Evolutionary Psychology (best overall performance in the MSc).
2008	UNIVERSITY OF LIVERPOOL – University of Liverpool International Scholarship.
	COLFUTURO – <u>Programa Crédito-Beca</u> .

#### **PUBLICACIONES**

#### Preprints 2019

Martínez, C. A., & **Leongómez**, **J.D.** (2019). Dehumanization Effects on Agency Attributions, Retributive Justice judgments, and Resocialization Attitudes towards Former Perpetrators in Post-conflict. *PsyArXiv*. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/w5tka

**Leongómez**, **J.D.**, Sanchez, O.R., Vasquez-Amezquita, M., Valderrama, E., Castellanos-Chacon, A., Morales-Sanchez, L., ... Gonzalez-Santoyo, I. (2019). Self-reported Health is Related to Body Height and Waist Circumference in Rural Indigenous and Urbanized Latin-American Populations. *BioRxiv*, 562942. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/562942">https://doi.org/10.1101/562942</a>

Publicados 2019

Vásquez-Amézquita, M., **Leongómez**, **J.D.**, Seto, M. C., Bonilla, M., Rodríguez-Padilla, A., & Salvador, A. (2019). Visual Attention Patterns Differ in Gynephilic and Androphilic Men and Women Depending on Age and Gender of Targets. *Journal of Sex Research*, 56(1), 85–101. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224499.2017.1372353

Vásquez Amézquita, M., **Leongómez**, **J.D.**, Seto, M. C., & Salvador, A. (2019). Differences in Visual Attention Patterns to Sexually Mature and Immature Stimuli Between Heterosexual Sexual Offenders, Nonsexual Offenders, and

- Nonoffending Men. *Journal of Sex Research*, 56(2), 213–228. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224499.2018.1511965
- Culpepper, P. D., Havlíček, J., **Leongómez**, **J.D.**, & Roberts, S. C. (in press). Visually activating pathogen disgust: A new instrument for studying the behavioural immune system. *Frontiers in Psychology*. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01397">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01397</a>
- Danel, D.P., Varella Valentova, J., Sánchez, O. R., Leongómez, J.D., Varella, M.A.C., Kleisner, K. (in press). A cross-cultural study of sex-typicality and averageness: Correlation between frontal and lateral measures of human faces. American Journal of Human Biology. Preprint available on bioRxiv (document 194662). https://doi.org/10.1101/194662
- Vásquez-Amézquita, M., **Leongómez**, **J.D.**, Seto, M. C., Bonilla, F. M., Rodríguez-Padilla, A., & Salvador, A. (2018). No relation between digit ratio (2D:4D) and visual attention patterns to sexually preferred and non-preferred stimuli. *Personality and Individual Differences*, 120, 151–158. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2017.08.022
- Mileva, V. R., & Leongómez, J.D. (2018, Marzo). Want to know if your partner's cheating on you? Just listen to their voice. *The Conversation*. Retrieved from <a href="https://theconversation.com/want-to-know-if-your-partners-cheating-on-you-just-listen-to-their-voice-92387">https://theconversation.com/want-to-know-if-your-partners-cheating-on-you-just-listen-to-their-voice-92387</a>
- Mileva, V. R., & Leongómez, J.D. (2017, Junio). We change our voice when we talk to high-status people, shows new study. *The Conversation*. Retrieved from <a href="https://theconversation.com/we-change-our-voice-when-we-talk-to-high-status-people-shows-new-study-80053">https://theconversation.com/we-change-our-voice-when-we-talk-to-high-status-people-shows-new-study-80053</a>
- **Leongómez**, **J.D.**, Mileva, V. R., Little, A. C., & Roberts, S. C. (2017). Perceived differences in social status between speaker and listener affect the speaker's vocal characteristics. *PLoS* One, 12(6), e0179407. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0179407">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0179407</a>
- Bonilla Carreño, C. F. M., & **Leongómez**, **J.D.** (2017). Efectos en la amplitud y la latencia del componente N170 ante la presenteación de rostros emocionales de ira y miedo. *Psychologia*, 11(1), 39–48. https://doi.org/10.21500/19002386.3100
- Cobey, K. D., Nicholls, M., **Leongómez**, **J.D.**, & Roberts, S. C. (2015). Self-reported Dominance in Women: Associations with Hormonal Contraceptive use, Relationship Status, and Testosterone. Adaptive Human Behavior and Physiology, 1(4), 449–459. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40750-015-0022-8
- Leongómez, J.D. (2015). La música como objeto de estudio científico: consideraciones en torno a la musicalidad y el origen de la música. Pensamiento Palabra Y Obra, 1(15), 77–86. https://doi.org/10.17227/2011804X.15PPO77.86
- **Leongómez**, **J.D.** (2014). Contextual Musicality: vocal modulation and its perception in human social interaction (Doctoral Thesis, University of Stirling, Reino Unido). Retrieved from http://hdl.handle.net/1893/21102

2018

2017

015

2014

Binter, J., Leongómez, J.D., Moyano, N., Valentova, J., Jouza, L., & Klapilová, K. (2012). Sex differences in the incidence of sexual fantasies focused on evolutionary relevant objects. Anthropologie: International Journal of Human **Diversity** and Evolution, 50(1), 83-93. http://puvodni.mzm.cz/Anthropologie/article.php?ID=1413

Ferdenzi, C., Lemaître, J.-F., Leongómez, J.D., & Roberts, S. C. (2011). Digit ratio (2D:4D) predicts facial, but not voice or body odour, attractiveness in men. Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 278(1724), 3551–3557. https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2011.0544

2008

Leongómez, J.D. (2008). El origen no humano de la música. (Pensamiento), (palabra) Υ Obra. 1. 87-97. Retrieved from https://dialnet.unirioja.es/servlet/articulo?codigo=3841084

2019

- Watkins, C.D., Leongómez, J.D., Bovet, J., Zelazniewicz, A., Korbmacher, M., Correa Varella, M.A., Fernandez, A.M., Wagstaff, D., & Bolgan, S. (2018). Do national health and wealth predict attitudes toward, and use of mouth-to-mouth kissing in romantic relationships? Manuscript under review.
- Martínez, C. A., & Leongómez, J.D. (2019). Dehumanization Effects on Agency Attributions, Retributive Justice judgments, and Resocialization Attitudes towards Former Perpetrators in Post-conflict. Manuscript under review.
- Leongómez, J.D., Sanchez, O.R., Vasquez-Amezquita, M., Valderrama, E., Castellanos-Chacon, A., Morales-Sanchez, L., ... Gonzalez-Santoyo, I. (2019). Self-reported Health is Related to Body Height and Waist Circumference in Rural Indigenous and Urbanized Latin-American Populations. Manuscript under review.

- Bonilla, F.M., Sánchez, O.R., Valderrama, E. & Mileva, V.R., & Leongómez, J.D. (2018). Effect of evolutionary relevant static signals (sex, dominance, and attractiveness) on cortical face processing humans. Manuscript in preparation
- Leongómez, J.D., Murray, A.K., & Roberts, S.C. (2018). Contextualising courtship: odour effects on vocal modulation. Manuscript in preparation.
- Binter, J., Leongómez, J.D., Sebesta, P., Bartova, K., Krejcova, L., Kubicova, L., Mueller, S., & Klapilova, K. (2017). Changes in testosterone, cortisol, and vocal displays during virtual courtship in Young adult men. Manuscript in preparation.
- Leongómez, J.D., & Roberts, S.C. (2017). Contextual musicality: a model for the evolution of human musicality. Manuscript in preparation.
- Leongómez, J.D., Sanchez, O.R., Valderrama, E., & Roberts, S. C. (2017). Masculinity and testosterone levels negatively predict pitch discrimination in men. Manuscript in preparation.
- Sanchez, O.R., Valderrama, E., Moreno, J., & Leongómez, J.D. (2017). Testosterone levels predict age of violent death in men and women across countries. Manuscript in preparation.

En preparación

Contextualising courtship: male body odour effects on vocal modulation; XXIV Biannual Conference for Human Ethology (Hotel Plaza San Francisco), Santiago,

Curso Corto de Posgrado (organizador y participante): Curso teórico-práctico en métodos y análisis de la forma mediante el empleo de la morfometría

Chile, September 3-7, 2018.

# CONFERENCIAS Y CURSOS

	There are in the second of the
	geométrica (Universidad El Bosque), Bogotá, Colombia, June 13 – 20, 2018.
2017	Efectos de los niveles hormonales, masculinidad y feminidad, en la discriminación
	tonal de hombres y mujeres; XXIII Congreso Institucional de Investigación
	(Universidad El Bosque), Bogotá, Colombia, Septiembre 20, 2017.
	El Sonido de la Seducción: Modulación vocal y sus efectos durante el cortejo; 2nd
	Simposio de Neurociencia, Cultura and Sociedad (Universidad Javeriana),
	Bogotá, Colombia, Agosto 18-19, 2017.
	¿Es la relación entre el procesamiento musical y lingüístico un vestigio de los
	orígenes evolutivos de la música? Brain Awareness Week 2017 (Universidad El
	Bosque), Bogotá, Colombia, Marzo 13, 2017.
2016	Perceived differences in social status between speaker and listener affect the
	speaker's vocal characteristics; International Society for Human Ethology (ISHE),
	XXIII Biennial Congress On Human Ethology (University of Stirling), Stirling, Reino
	Unido, Agosto 1-6, 2016.
2014	Vocal modulation during courtship increases proceptivity even in naive listeners;
	European Human Behaviour and Evolution Association, EHBEA Annual Meeting
	2014 (University of Bristol), Bristol, Reino Unido, Abril 6-9, 2014.
2013	The sound of sweet nothings: How men and women modulate vocal parameters in
	speech directed towards attractive and unattractive individuals. The Social
	Mind and Brain Group (University of Stirling), Stirling, Reino Unido, Abril 4, 2013.
	Poster: European Human Behaviour and Evolution Association, EHBEA Annual
	Meeting 2013 (VU University Amsterdam), Amsterdam, Holanda, Marzo 24-27
	2013.
	Voice research techniques using Praat; (Faculty of Humanities, Charles University),
	Praga, República Checa, Marzo 15, 2013.
	Evolutionary psychology and research; (Faculty of Humanities, Charles University),
	Praga, República Checa, Marzo 11, 2013.
	Acoustic Communication; (Centre for Theoretical Study), Praga, República Checa,
0010	Marzo 5, 2013.
2012	Short Course: Statistical Programming in R and Linear Mixed Models (University of
	Dundee), Dundee, Reino Unido, August 27 – 29, 2012.  The sounds of sweet nothings: human yeard modulations and courtship: Crown of
	The sounds of sweet nothings: human vocal modulations and courtship; Group of Human Ethology (Charles University), Praga, República Checa, Mayo 23, 2012.
	Homan Emology (Challes onliversity), Maya, Republica Checa, Mayo 25, 2012.

- Voice research techniques using Praat; Group of Human Ethology (Charles University), Praga, República Checa, Mayo 16, 2012.
- Voice research techniques using Praat; Scottish Universities Psychology Postgraduate Research Training SUPPORT (University of Stirling), Stirling, Reino Unido, January 25, 2012.
- Virtual Conference: The sound of seduction: How men and women modulate our vocal parameters when speaking with attractive or unattractive individuals; Psychology (Universidad El Bosque), Bogotá, Colombia, Noviembre 3, 2011.
- The sound of sweet nothings: How men and women modulate vocal parameters in speech directed towards attractive and unattractive individuals; Behaviour and Evolution Research Group (University of Stirling), Stirling, Reino Unido, Febrero 23, 2011.
- Poster: Context-dependent modulation of vocal parameters; The Language of Music, the Music of Language; Meeting 2: Entrainment/Meaning (Centre for Music & Science, University of Cambridge), Cambridge, Reino Unido, Diciembre 13-14, 2010.

# REFERENCIAS ACADÉMICAS

- **Prof. S. CRAIG ROBERTS (Ph.D.)** University of Stirling, School of Natural Sciences (Reino Unido). <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/people/10925">https://www.scraigroberts.com/</a>
- **Prof. PHYLLIS C. LEE (Ph.D.)** University of Stirling, School of Natural Sciences (Reino Unido). <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/people/11303">https://www.stir.ac.uk/people/11303</a>.
- **Prof. JAN HAVLÍČEK (Ph.D.)** Charles University, Faculty of Science (República Checa). https://www.scopus.com/authid/detail.uri?authorld=7004768243.